<?xml version="1.0"?> <!-- -*- sgml -*- -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="mainwindow" xreflabel="The Main Window">
<title>The Main Window</title>

<para>The main window is composed of several elements, explanations for
which are below.</para>


<sect1 id="menu_bar" xreflabel="The MenuBar">
<title>The MenuBar</title>


<sect2 id="file_menu" xreflabel="The File Menu">
<title>The File Menu</title>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem id="run_button">
    <para><command>File->Run Valgrind:</command></para>
    <para>This option will be disabled if a process is currently
    running.</para>s
    <para>Selecting this option will run Valgrind on whatever executable 
    is currently specified in the Options::Valkyrie::Binary option.
    If no executable has been set, a dialog will pop up asking you to 
    enter the path/to/executable.</para>
    <para>The "Run Valgrind" toolbutton is a shortcut to this menu option.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem id="stop_button">
    <para><command>File->Stop:</command></para>
    <para>This option will be disabled unless a process is currently
    running.</para>
    <para>Selecting this option will abort the current run.</para>
    <para>Note: Not all processes can currently be stopped: for example
    loading/saving a logfile.</para>
    <para>The "Stop" toolbutton is a shortcut to this menu option.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><command>File->Close:</command></para>
    <para>Selecting this will close the current ToolView.  If the ToolView
    contains an unsaved file, or if a process is in the middle of being run,
    a dialog will pop up asking for confirmation.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><command>File->Exit:</command></para>
    <para>Exits Valkyrie.  If a process is in the middle of being run, 
    or a ToolView contains unsaved data, a dialog will pop up asking for 
    confirmation.</para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="tools_menu" xreflabel="The Tools Menu">
<title>The Tools Menu</title>

<itemizedlist id="tview_buttons">
  <listitem>
    <para>This menu shows which Valgrind tools are available.  The currently 
    selected tool is greyed out.</para>
    <para>The "ToolView Buttons" at the bottom, just below the status
    message area, provide a quick way of switching between views. The
    currently selected ToolView button is depressed.</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="options_menu" xreflabel="The Options Menu">
<title>The Options Menu</title>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>This menu contains links to a dialog where preferences, options and 
    flags may be set for Valkyrie, Valgrind, and (supported) Valgrind tools.
    Any flag which may be given on the command-line for Valkyrie or Valgrind
    is available to be set in this dialog.  Settings applied to the current
    run are only saved to disk if you select Options->Save As Default.
    Also see <xref linkend="context_help"/> below.</para>
    <para>For detailed information on this dialog, see the 
    <xref linkend="options_dialog"/> page.</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

  

<sect2 id="help_menu" xreflabel="The Help Menu">
<title>The Help Menu</title>

<itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
    <para><command>Handbook</command></para>
    <para>You can access the HandBook at any time.  It contains the manuals 
    for both Valgrind and Valkyrie.  See also 
    <xref linkend="context_help"/> below.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><command>About Dialog</command></para>
    <para>This is a small dialog with brief "about" information.</para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>



<sect2 id="context_help" xreflabel="Context Help">
<title>Context Help</title>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>When clicked, the cursor will change its shape; then, clicking 
    on any widget anywhere within Valkyrie will bring up the "Handbook" 
    at the relevant page, providing instant help without having to trawl 
    through the manual.</para>
    <para>This is particularly useful for the
    <xref linkend="options_dialog"/> box: Clicking on a option widget
    will take you directly to the relevant section of the manual.</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

</sect1>

  

  
  
<sect1 id="mainwindow.vg_ctl_tool_bar" xreflabel="Valgrind Control ToolBar">
<title>Valgrind Control ToolBar</title>

<para>This toolbar simply holds shortcut buttons to the File->Run Valgrind,
and File->Stop menu options.</para>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="mainwindow.tool_bar" xreflabel="ToolView ToolBar">
<title>ToolView ToolBar</title>

<para>Each ToolView has its own toolbar, giving various options for
that Valgrind tool.  See the appropriate tool`s section of the manual for
information on its toolbars.</para>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="mainwindow.tool_view" xreflabel="ToolViews">
<title>ToolViews</title>

<para>The current ToolView resides in the main central area.
Each ToolView has its own specific window with different functionality.
For example, MemcheckView provides a tree-view showing the parsed
XML output of Valgrind.</para>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="mainwindow.flags_widget" xreflabel="Flags Widget">
<title>Flags Widget</title>

<para>The flags widget shows the flags for the current Valgrind process.
A button to open/close the flags widget is on the bottom right corner,
with an icon of a flag.</para>

<para>Example: if <computeroutput>valkyrie /bin/ls -lF</computeroutput> 
was given on the command line, then this window would show:</para>
<programlisting>
    /path/to/valgrind 
    --tool=memcheck 
    --xml=yes 
    /bin/ls -lF
</programlisting>

<para>Note: Valkyrie only displays and sends flags to Valgrind which are
not the defaults.</para>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="mainwindow.status_msg" xreflabel="Status Messages">
<title>Status Messages</title>

<para>Messages are displayed here, showing the current state of play.</para>

</sect1>


</chapter>
