<?xml version="1.0"?> <!-- -*- sgml -*- -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="options" xreflabel="Options Dialog">
<title>Options Dialog</title>


The Options dialog has a separate "pane" for each valgrind tool, as well
as for Valkyrie and Valgrind.  Any flag or option which can be set on
the command line for valgrind or any valgrind tool is available.

On first-time startup, all options are set to their defaults.  If you 
subsequently change any of these, for example by giving the following on 
the command line:
  ./bin/valkyrie --show-reachable=yes /bin/ls -lF
then the value of the argument will be saved, and the option will then
be set to this value until you specifically change it again.

Note: choosing "Reset Defaults" will reset the default values for
*all* the options pages, not just the current one.



- Valkyrie Options Page

Show tooltips
  Whether tooltips should be shown when the mouse pointer hovers over a widget.
  Applied application-wide.

Show toolbar text labels
  Whether text labels should be shown next to buttons.  Applied application-wide.

Use default system font
  Whether valkyrie should use your default window font or not.
  Clicking "Choose" will bring up a font dialog to allow you to select
  an alternative font.  Applied application-wide.

Use valkyrie's palette
  Whether valkyrie should use your default window palette (aka "theme") or
  use her own.  Applied application-wide.

Extra lines shown above/below the target line
  Memcheck-specific.  This value specifies the number of source code lines to 
  be shown above and below the target source line when displaying errors
  in Memcheck ToolView.  Note that changing this value will not take effect
  until the next run.

Source editor:
  Memcheck-specific.  Specify the /path/to/your/favourite/editor.
  The editor is launched when a stack frame is double-clicked within 
  Memcheck ToolView.

Binary:
  Change the name of the executable to run to /path/to/your/executable.
  If you started valkyrie on the command line with "valkyrie /path/to/exe"
  then "/path/to/exe" is stored here.

Binary flags:
  Change the flags relevant to your executable. If you started valkyrie
  on the command line with "valkyrie /path/to/your/exe --your-flags" then 
  "--your-flags" is stored here.

Valgrind:
  This is the /path/to/valgrind which you specified when you configured 
  and built valkyrie.  It is shown here purely for information purposes.

Supps Dir:
  This is the /path/to/valgrind/suppressions/dir which you specified
  when you configured and built valkyrie.  It is shown here purely for
  information purposes.

  If you want to add/remove/change the suppression files, see
  <Suppression Files>.



- Valgrind Options Page

  Valgrind's options page has been divided into three areas which reflect
  the split between Core options, Error Reporting options, and suppressions.

  To access valgrind's manual for help on any of these options, click on
  the <Context Help> toolbutton and then click on the relevant widget.

  Suppressions tab
  On first-time install, the bottom listbox contains valgrind's default 
  suppression files.  The top listbox only contains one file "default.supp".

  Right-clicking on either the top or bottom listbox will bring up a popup 
  menu allowing you to modify the list of files.
  
 
- Valgrind Tool Options Pages

  There is an option page for each tool which is supported by valkyrie.
  Currently, this is only Memcheck; although the pages for Cachegrind and 
  Massif have been implemented, they are not functional.

  To access valgrind's manual for help on any of these options, click on
  the <Context Help> toolbutton and then click on the relevant widget
  on a Tool's Options page.
